<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An advertisement to everie Godly reader of Mr. Thomas Brightman his book. namely [sic], A revelation of the apocalyps. In which advertisement is shewed how corruptly he teacheth, that notwithstanding all the sinns &amp; abhominations that are in the Church of England, and by him shewed, yet that it is blasphemous to separate from it</title>
            <author>L'Écluse, Jean de.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1612</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A72529</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15351.7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S124557</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99899174</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99899174</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150666</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A72529)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150666)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1967:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An advertisement to everie Godly reader of Mr. Thomas Brightman his book. namely [sic], A revelation of the apocalyps. In which advertisement is shewed how corruptly he teacheth, that notwithstanding all the sinns &amp; abhominations that are in the Church of England, and by him shewed, yet that it is blasphemous to separate from it</title>
                  <author>L'Écluse, Jean de.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>G. Thorp],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Amsterdam :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Imprinted in the year 1612.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The epistle to the reader is signed: Iean de Lescluse.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Caption title on p. 5: An advertisement concerning M. Brightman upon the Apocalyps.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Lincoln College Library, Oxford, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Brightman, Thomas, 1562-1607. --  Revelation of the Apocalyps --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Revelation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:150666:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>AN</hi> ADVERTISEMENT TO EVERIE GODLY READER OF Mr. Thomas Brightman his book. namely, <hi>A REVELATION OF THE APOCALYPS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which advertiſement is ſhewed how corruptly he tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth, that notwithſtanding all the ſinns &amp; abhominations that are in the Church of England, and by him ſhewed, yet that it is blaſphemous to ſeparate from it.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 King. 18.21.</hi>
               </bibl> How long halt yee between two opinions? If the Lord be God, follow him: but if Baal be he, then go after him.</q>
            <p>Imprinted in the yere 1612.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:150666:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:150666:2"/>
            <head>AN EPISTLE To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, the cauſes that have moved mee to put forth this ſhort writing, are cheifly three; the first, the glory of the Lord my God,<note place="margin">Lev. 19.2. 1 Pet. 1.15.16.</note> who as he is holy, ſo dooth he require that all his people ſhould be holy, in all manner of converſation: and that all thoſe that call upon the name of Chriſt ſhould depart from iniquity. <hi>2 Tim. 2.19.</hi> The ſecond, the fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent deſire which I have of the ſalvation of mens ſoules, &amp; gayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of them unto God; the means whereof being,<note place="margin">Iam. 5.19.20.</note> in ſhewing unto them their erring from the truth, and to convert them from go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing astray, out of the way. The third, is in reſpect of my ſelf; for having had a hand both in the tranſlating and printing of M. B. book, and there being in it, as I am fully perſwaded, &amp; as by the grace of God I ſhal ſhew, out of the holy ſcriptures, errors and abberations from the truth of the living God; If I had held my peace and ſayd nothing, I could not have cleared my ſelf from partaking with other mens ſynns; and ſo ſhould have done, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary unto that holy commandement of the Apoſtle to Timothy.<note place="margin">1 Tim. 5.22</note>
            </p>
            <p>To the end therfore, that the reader may the better perceive the thing intended in this writing, namely, how corruptly Mr. Brightman, dooth teach, not to ſeparate fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Church of Engl. notwithſtanding all the corruptions which he ſhewes to be in her; this is the order that I ſhall obſerve, to wit, that firſt I will ſet down ſome of the particulars wherby he blames that Church of England, for partaking with the corruptions and manner of government of Antichriſt. Secondly I ſhall ſhew ſome of the praiſes, which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding theſe corruptions, he gives vnto the ſame. And thirdly what is the collection or concluſion that he gathers therevp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: which having done <hi>I</hi> ſhal alſo declare my mind concerning theſe things. And thus (Christian Reader) I ſhall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving, or cenſuring of all, to thy godly wiſdom, grounded upon the canon and holy writings of the holy Prophets and Apoſtles. Fare well.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine as thou art the Lords <hi>Iean de Leſcluſe.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:150666:3"/>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:150666:3"/>
            <head>An Advertiſement concerning M. Brightman upon the Apocalyps.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or to come therfore unto the matter I will begin with that which is written in the 103 page of his book, tranſlated into Engliſh, where he ſhewed the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> moſt fearfull eſtate of the Church of England in theſe words: <hi>I could not but mourn from the bottome of myne heart when I beheld in her, Chriſt</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">faſtidien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem.</note> 
               <hi>lothing us, and very greatly provoked againſt us.</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond blame which he layeth vpon the back of the Church of England is, that the <hi>moſt mighty King Henry had expelled the Pope, but <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> reteyned the popiſh ſuperstition;</hi> pag. 104 of the ſayd book.</p>
            <p>The third evil wherwith he chargeth that Church of England is, that <hi>there is ſuch a form of Church establiſhed as is neyther cold nor hot, but ſet in the middes, and made of both:</hi> and againe in the ſame place about 2. or 3 lines after he hath theſe words: <hi>Hot in deed ſhe is not, whoſe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward government for the moſt part is yet ſtil Romiſh: In the degrees of their Clergie, in Elections, and ordinations, and whole administration of the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures: which</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio purio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae.</note> 
               <hi>mixing of the pure doctrine, and Romiſh regiment togither, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth this lukewarmnes, wherby wee ſtand in the middes between cold and hot, between the Romiſh and the reformed Churches, of both which wee are</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">confla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur.</note> 
               <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed:</hi> and a few lines after he produceth the teſtimony of the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and godly, Martin Bucer, in a letter of his written to a freind at Cambridge in the yeare 1550, where he complayneth of the corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption of the Church of England, in theſe words; <hi>There be ſome who by moſt humane wiſdome and vaniſhing cogitations, would joyn togither God and Belial, by the leaven of Antichriſt:</hi> Such are the words of Martin Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer: which are thus confirmed by Mr Brightmans: <hi>Theſe things he did write, which wee at this day find by experience too true.</hi> pa. 108. of his book.</p>
            <p n="4">4. He maketh the condition of the poor blinde Papiſts, to be farr <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IIII"/> better, then the condition of the Angels of the Church of England; in theſe words, <hi>for in this place Chriſt preferreth the blinde Papists, before thoſe Angels, who bewitched with ambition and covetouſnes, doe refuſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reformation.</hi> pag. 109. And in the 111 pag, ſpeaking of the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment to be inflicted upon this Engliſh Angel for his ſinnes, he ſpeaketh alſo thus of the whole Church. <hi>It is alſo to be feared, that the Church may feele ſome adverſitie through contagion and conſenting to. Such as are the Angels, ſuch becometh ſhee for the most part: and none is ſo igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the matters, that ſeeth not playnly, that the whole body is ſick of the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:150666:4"/> ſame diſeaſe.</hi> And ſo by his own grant, the whole ſtate of that Church to be worſe then that of the Church of Rome.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> 5. In the 112 page be ſheweth what is the cauſe of the lukewarm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the Church of England in theſe words: <hi>Jn our England the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruency is ſo manifeſt, that nothing could have been expreſſed more lively: for what other cauſe can wee bring of our lukewarmnes, the Popiſh government mingled with the pure doctrine then the love of riches and honours?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VI"/> 6. Obſerve alſo in the ſame page a ſhort deſcription of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel of the Church of Engl. in theſe words. <hi>But our Biſhops are Peeres of the Realme, ſuperiour in honour to many great ſtates: alſo in riches, compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of men and mayd ſervants, in magnificence of howſes, and all the other pomp of the world, equal to any, even the greateſt Earles. How rich is the reſt of the Clergie? The Deanes, Arch-deacons, Prebendaries, Chaplains,</hi> &amp;c. And that theſe and the like are the Angel of the Church of England wherof he ſpeaketh ſo often in this book, it appeareth by that wich foloweth in the beginning of the page 113 in theſe words: <hi>Doe not this amplify and increaſe very greatly the glory of the Church, that her Ministers do ſhine in garments of ſilk and velvet.</hi> &amp;c. and alſo by that which is in pag. 117. thus, <hi>Thou art therfore a begger ô thou Engliſh An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel:</hi> comprehending under the name of this Engliſh Angel, which he calls a <hi>begger, Curates, Prebendaries, Archdeacons, Deacons,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Biſhops</hi> themſelves, as it may be plainly ſeen in the 116 and 117 pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of his book, in which places obſerve alſo by the way, the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of entrance into the Miniſtery of the Church of England, plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſcribed by Mr Brightmans.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VII"/> 7. The ſeventh charge wherewith he dealeth with the Church of Engl. is to be ſeen in the 116 pa. thus: <hi>So reprehenſions are ſilent,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">nequitia regnat.</note> 
               <hi>naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines reigneth, the hand of God is heavy upon us, and whither the matter will grow at laſt, prudent men feare not without iuſt cauſe.</hi> With which is to be added that which he ſayth in the pag. 117, namely that the lawes of Chriſt are not kept in the Ch: of Engl. in theſe words: <hi>wee avayle nothing with our Lawes; where the lawes of Chriſt are not kept.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VIII"/> 8. In the pag 119. he obſerveth, that the ordinances concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the manner of entrance into the Miniſtery of the Church of England is ſuch, as for which the other reformed Churches may be aſhamed: thus, <hi>Excellent ordinances in deed; for which the reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches may be aſhamed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IX"/> 9 He chargeth this Church to have ſuch officers as whoſe names,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:150666:4"/> except the Biſhop have not been heard in the Church: thus, <hi>What is this auncient uſe of pronouncing the ſentence by them, whoſe names, except onely the Biſhop, have not been heard in deed in the Church, as long as the true honour and dignity of excommunication remayned?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The tenth and laſt charge of his, which I doo here purpoſe to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="X"/> adde, leaving the reſt, becauſe it were too long to relate them all in particular ſhalbe this, written in the pag 128. of his book, where he makes the Angel of the Church of Engl. a perſecuter of the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren &amp; a deceiver of the Prince. Thus, <hi>Repent of the iniuries which thou haſt done to the brethren, in caſting ſome into priſon, in turning others out of their goods, in depriving many of the power to preach the word, in reproching and traducing all with the odious names of Anabaptiſts</hi> &amp;c. and in the ſame page a few lines after; thus he ſpeaketh, <hi>That was a notable ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnie, whereby both thou haſt deceived the PRINCE, and alſo haſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured hatred to the brethren:</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Theſe &amp; many the like charges are in his book, wherby he ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the fearfulnes of the eſtate of the Church of England.</p>
            <p>Now followeth to ſhew breifly ſome of the prayſes which he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo giveth vnto her, wherby as with a ſalve, he cureth all her ſoares.</p>
            <p>And firſt in the very title of his Epiſtle dedicatory to the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> thus he writeth, <hi>To the holy reformed Churches of</hi> &amp;c. where note that the Church of Britany, that is the Church of England hath this honourable title given her with the reſt, <hi>holy reformed:</hi> vnto which title add that which alſo he ſaith in the 102 pag. of this book, where he maketh the Church of England to be the Antitype of the Church of Laodicea, thus; <hi>The Antitype is the third reformed Church;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond good thing which he ſheweth to be in the Church <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> and Kingdome of England is twofold,<note place="margin">double bleſſings in the Church of Engl.</note> in the 104 &amp; 105 pages of his book; the firſt in reſpect of earthly bleſſings: the ſecond in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of ſpiritual: for the firſt thus he ſpeaketh: <hi>From hence the lawes are in force, judgements are exerciſed, every one inioyeth his own; iniuries are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayned; wantonnes is repreſsed,</hi> &amp;c. The ſecond is thus,<note place="margin">Earthly.</note> 
               <hi>And to what end were all theſe good things if we could not have the wholſom doctrine of truth?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Spiritual.</note> 
               <hi>But ever ſince the first times of our moſt peaceable Queen, he hath rayſed up continually deligent and learned Paſtours &amp; Teachers, who have preached the word purely and ſyncerely. Neyther at this day are wanting many, by his infinite mercy, who bestow all their labour in imparting to his people the whole will of God, and that pure and uncorrupt from all leaven of falſhood.</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:150666:5"/> Adde vnto this alſo the ſanctification of theſe Paſtours by Chriſt in the 106 page, thus; <hi>But he that is a faithfull and true witneſs, ſanctifieth the Paſtours with the truth beyond all hope: in whoſe lipps he dwelleth even hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto:</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> 3. But in the page 318 he is large in deſcribing the good eſtate of the Church of England thus: <hi>as it came to paſs in our England, to which Christ at the ſound of the ſeventh trumpet, in the yere 1558, gave the most gracious Queen Elizabeth, who againe gave her Kingdome to Christ, in roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out through all her dominions, the moſt part of the Romiſh ſuperſtitions, and in reſtoring to her people the ſyncere and wholeſome truth, that wee might worſhip the Lord our God according to his ordinance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IIII"/> The fourth good thing which he mentioneth to be in the Church of England, is the preaching of the word &amp; the lawfull adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſacraments, in theſe words; <hi>Theſe things therfore doo proove, that a double and great good thing doo abide in the Engliſh Church, that is to ſay, the preaching of the word, and the lawful adminiſtration of the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: In both which Christ bestoweth himſelf vpon his people, keeping a mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual feast with them, he firſt being received of us by hearing of the word; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, entertayning us againe with the ſupper of his body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus much touching ſome of the praiſes which he giveth unto that Church of England: now let the godly ſee in theſe words of his following, what concluſion he maketh hereupon; which may be read in the 131 pag. of his book thus: <hi>Therfore wicked and blaſphemous is their errour, who doo fall away ſo from this Church, as if Chriſt were baniſhed wholly from hence; and that there could not be any hope of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation for them that tarry there. Let them mind here Chriſt feasting with his people. Wil they be aſhamed to ſit down there, where they ſee Chriſt not to be aſhamed? Are they purer and holyer then he?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Theſe things being thus ſet down, it reſteth now that according to my promiſe, I doo alſo ſhew my mind concerning them? thus therefore, firſt to begin with that which I have ſet for the firſt charge, which he layeth upon the Church of England; I deſire the reader to obſerve the word which he uſeth of Chriſt <hi>loathing them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">faſtidien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem noſtri.</note> which word of loathing ſeemeth to be taken from the <hi>95.</hi> Pſal. ver. 10. where the Prophet ſpeaking in the perſon of the Lord himſelf, ſayth that fowrty yeres long he had loathed that generation: ſaying that they are a people erring in heart, and not knowing his wayes, wherfore he ſware in his wrath that they ſhould not enter into his
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:150666:5"/> reſt. So that by M. Brightmans own graunt this Church of England is in no better eſtate then were thoſe rebels in the wildernes, all which were conſumed and entred not into his reſt, as he had ſworn.</p>
            <p>But that the Lord hath more juſt cauſe to loath the Church of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, then that of the Iſraelites in the wildernes, let the reader ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it in theſe particulars; firſt that that Church had a true Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and true Offices and Officers; and ſo hath not the Church of England by M. Brightmans own graunt: Secondly the Officers of that Church never perſecuted the faithful Iewes for practiſing the holy ordinances of God; as he affirmeth that the Angel of the Ch: of England dooth, thoſe that will not ſubmit to their government. Thirdly, their government was not a mixt government partly of the Aegyptians, partly of the Moabites, and Edomites or Cananeans, but ſimple and pure according to the true patern ſhewed to Moſes in the mount: but that of England is not ſo, for Mr Brightman af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth it to be partly Romiſh and partly reformed, and ſo not the true government which Chriſt hath appointed in his eternall Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Fourthly, none of that Church were admitted unto any of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice but onely ſuch as were lawfully called thereunto as Aaron was, but ſo it is not in the Church of England, for ſuch Offices and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers are there admitted as are unknown unto the true Church of Chriſt by Mr Brightmans own doctrine. Therfore it dooth neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily follow that the eſtate of the Church of England is worſe then was the eſtate of thoſe rebels in the wildernes, and that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be expected from Chriſt, by any member thereof, but a powring out of his eternall wrath upon them.</p>
            <p>Concerning his ſecond charge of King Henry expelling the Pope but reteyning the popiſh ſuperſtition; this is that which I ſay, that the Pope cannot properly be ſaid to be expelled when his doctrine &amp; ſuperſtition is reteyned; for as concerning the Popes own perſon he could not be expelled from England for he was never there. But it may be that Mr Brightman meaneth that ſome of the Monks &amp; Fryars were driven out and their revenues taken away from them; as alſo that their manner of worſhipping of God which was in the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin tongue, was then tranſlated into Engliſh: but what of all this? can this be ſayd to be an expelling of the Pope? No; for in deed &amp; properly, it is the doctrine &amp; ſuperſtition of the Pope which dooth corrupt the harts and ſoules of men, which can be done eyther in a
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:150666:6"/> Kingdome or in a Province or in a pariſh, or in a houſe without the preſence eyther of the Pope himſelfe or of any of his Monks and Fryars, by their doctrine, ſuperſtitions, falſe manner of worſhip, which are ſpred too farre abroad in the world by their bookes and writings, and even now reteyned <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o this day in England, as Mr. Brightman himſelf do write.</p>
            <p>The third is that the eſtabliſhed form of the Church of England is neyther cold nor hot, and againe, that ſhe is not hot whoſe outward government for the moſt part is yet ſtill Romiſh; and againe that this mixing of the pure doctrine and Romiſh government togither maketh this lukewarmnes; wherby they ſtand between cold and hot, between the Romiſh and the reformed Churches, of both which they are compoſed: joyn with this th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> which wee have ſet for the fift charge where he ſayth, that <hi>no other cauſe can be brought of their luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warmnes, the Popiſh government mingled with the pure doctrine, then the love of riches and honours?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I beſeech the reader to compare this with his firſt prayſe of the Church of England which is in the very title of his Epiſtle dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catory, where he intituled the Church of England to be a reformed Church. Is it poſſible that holynes and unholynes can raigne togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? Is there any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion between Chriſt and Antichriſt? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween light and darknes? between Idols and the true God? Can a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Kingdome, any Church, any family, any man ſubmit unto the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, of Antichriſt and not be defiled therby? No God himſelf and his Prophets; Chriſt and his Apoſtles doo teach otherwiſe, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let all ſuch as do ſo teach, remember that ſaying of the Prophet Iſayas, <hi>Woe unto him that calleth evil good,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Moreover in his fourth charge where he maketh the ſtate of the poor blinde Papiſts farr better, then the condition of the Angel of the Church of England, and that alſo ſuch as are the Angels ſuch be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth the Church for the moſt part, I doe obſerve that by his own doctrine the eſtate of the Church of England is worſe then Babylon it ſelf; which Babylon is granted by all to be that Synagogue and Church of Antichriſt devoted unto deſtruction in the day of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall wrath of the Lamb. And where are then thoſe great prayſes of all manner of bleſſings upon that Church reherſed in the ſecond article, but cheifly theſe ſpirituall bleſſings of the word purely and ſyncerely taught in it? Yea in that Church of which he ſaith in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:150666:6"/> the ſeventh article of his charges, that <hi>naughtynes raigneth</hi> in it, the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of God is heavie upon it and agayn, that in her the lawes of Chriſt are not kept. But what is there then to be done, even this, that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſoule who hath any care of ſalvation and of eſcaping the eternall flames of everlaſting damnation be careful to come out with ſpeed from Babylon and not to partake any longer with her ſinnes, leaſt they patake alſo of her plagues. For it is unpoſſible to be both a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly member of Chriſt, and worſe then a Papiſt; Chriſt nor his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers cannot be coupled with a harlot and her members, &amp; whoſoever coupleth himſelf with a harlot, is made one body with her, as wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth the holy Apoſtle.</p>
            <p>As concerning therfore the outward bleſſings of peace and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity in earthly things, let every godly mind that by it no Church, no man, can have any aſſurance to be in the favour of God: but let every ſoul be ſure that where there is no repentance from evil works they are but fatlings againſt the day of ſlaughter.</p>
            <p>But becauſe I doe ſee that this writing enlargeth it ſelf beyond that which I had determined, I ſhall now begin to draw to an end con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his charges againſt the Church of England and the Angel therof: and therfore wil here bring the reſt into a ſhort ſumme, and they at theſe, firſt, that the entra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce into the Miniſtery of the Church of England is ſuch as for which the other reformed Churches may be aſhamed: ſecondly that the names of the officers of that Church have not been heard in the Church, but onely the Biſhops; finally that the Angel of that Church, is both a perſecuter of the brethren, and a deceiver of the Prince: when I doe conſider theſe things and others alſo which I have both ſeen and heard, I cannot but lament &amp; deplore the eſtate both of thoſe moſt noble Princes of England as alſo of their poore ſubjects, which are thus miſuſed by thoſe ſonns of Anak though I be but a ſtranger unto them and under the juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of an other Prince. It is now 46 yeres agoe that indeed the reformed Churches began to be aſhamed of ſome things which they had but heard concerning the eſtate of the Church of England, as namely <hi>the plurality of benefices, licences of non reſidency, licences to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract mariages, the vſe of meats</hi> and the like, which things they then jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, not to be a corruption of Chriſtianity, but a manifeſt apoſtaſy from Chriſt: for which ſee my countryman of famous &amp; happy me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory Theodorus Beza in his Epiſtle to Edmu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Grindal then Biſhop
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:150666:7"/> of London. <hi>Epiſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> towards the end. And if theſe things were thus written ſo many yeres agoe, what may all the reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches now ſay of the eſtate of that of England which they have as yet embraced as their ſiſter hitherto, when they ſhall both ſee &amp; know by this man even a profeſſed freind of hers, thus to ſpeak, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning her eſtate: But yet concerning this point I muſt needs ſay, that in deed the reformed Churches have not dealt with that Church of England ſo ſyncerely &amp; playnly as they ſhould have done. For what is it, if one or two of the moſt famous members of them have thus in a few words and as it were by the way ſet down ſome few of her corruptions? Have they not many thowſands of them both learned and unlearned, ſeen and heard the eſtate of the officers of that Ch: to be Antichriſtian? &amp; that the very ofſpring of every one of them is from the Archbiſhops, which very name may not be attributed unto any eyther man or Angel without blaſphemy againſt Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus who is the alone head and cheif of all Biſhops and Paſtours? Have they not alſo ſeen that the manner of worſhipping God in their Cathedral Churches, as they call them, with ſinging men, and ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing boyes cloathed with white ſurplices, with Orgens and all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of muſique? Have they not ſeen and heard that all manner of wicked livers both Papiſts and others are compelled to partake with the reſt, and of a confuſed multitude, to make the Church and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſt, and ſo force and compel men to take their condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and judgment? Have they not alſo heard and known that the Archbiſhops and Biſhops and others of the officers of that Church have ſo many yeeres continually oppoſed and ſhewed themſelves to be deadly enemies unto all godly reformation? Yea doubtles, they doo know and have known all theſe things and many more: But how have they dealt in this reſpect? Have they at any time Chriſtian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; ſoundly admoniſhed, reproved, convinced that Church of their corruptions by the lawe and word of God as they ought to have done? not at al; but they have rather eyther held their peace or flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered them in their ſinns, or ſo little ſpoken or written of them, as that they may well and juſtly be aſhamed, of their unkindnes in this reſpect towards that Kingdome and people of whom they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived ſo many benefits in tyme of their calamities &amp; baniſhments. Concerning the names of the officers of that Church, they were (ſayth he) unknown unto the Church of Chriſt. &amp;c. And what is
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:150666:7"/> this? Shal then any ſoule in whome there is but a very ſmall ſparkle of the feare of God, be ſo bold as to dare ſubmitt under the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and guidance of ſuch vnlawfull Miniſters and Miniſtery? Are they not all thieves &amp; robbers which enter not in by the doore, but climbe up another way? And will any man of wiſdome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit unto the protection and keeping of thieves the leaſt part of his worldly goods? No, none wilbe ſo unwiſe, for every one knoweth that they wil but make a pray of them and ſpoile and robbe them. And ſhall any then be ſo carefull for things of ſo ſmall importance, and ſhall he not care unto whom he dooth commit the guidance of that which is the principall, namely of his ſoule? Let them alone therfore, for as our ſaviour Chriſt ſayth, they are blind leaders of the blind: and both of them ſhall ſurely fall into the pit.</p>
            <p>Finally, the Angel of the Church of England is both a perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the brethren and a deceiver of the Prince. Marvelous; and is he ſtill for all this, the Angel of the Church in Mr. Brightmans judgement? In mine doubtleſſe he is altogither otherwiſe; even that Angel of the bottomleſſe pit, who is a King over thoſe Locuſts ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of in the ninth of the Revelation; like unto that wicked Haman ſpoken of in the book of Eſther who both perſecuted the brethren of the Church of God, and alſo deceived the King: but let theſe take heed, for God who hath the hearts of Kings &amp; Princes in his hands for to turn them as the Rivers of waters, ſhall no doubt diſcover the malice of this Angel unto the Princes of that land, and then ſhall they be rewarded as Haman was<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Beſides let every godly Reader obſerve, that to be a perſecuter of Gods people and ſaints, is and hath been alwayes a ſure mark of Antichriſt and of his kingdome.</p>
            <p>To conclude therfore this writing, I wil come unto that which wee have ſet for the fourth prayſe of the Church of England, and the concluſions that he dooth inferr therupon, which are theſe. <hi>Theſe things therfore proove that a double and great good thing dooth abide in the Engliſh Church, that is to ſay, the preaching of the word, and the lawfull admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistration of the ſacraments:</hi> &amp;c. his 2. concluſion followeth therupon thus: <hi>Therfore wicked and blaſphemous is their errour, who doo ſo fall away from this Church as if Christ were baniſhed wholly from hence.</hi> &amp;c. And ſo by this whatſoever ſinns, errours, wickedneſſes abhominations, he hath ſhewed before to be, both in the Angel and in the Church it ſelf, all is now cured by this ſalve: ô moſt miſerable dawbing with
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:150666:8"/> untempered morter! Can any preach in the office of an Angel purely and ſyncerely who is a theife and a robber? Shal any man adminiſter purely, who is not lawfully called therunto as Aaron was? Can any unlawfull miniſter adminiſter lawfully the ſeales of Gods Covenant unto doggs and ſwyne purely and ſincerely? O ceaſe to doe evill &amp; learne to doe good! God who is jealous of his honour and glory ſhall not long ſuffer this wickednes unpuniſhed. Are the bodies of Idolatrous Papiſts, or abhominable whores and whoremongers and of all manner of wicked ones, the temples of the holy Ghoſt? No; who ſoever coupleth himſelf with a harlot is made one body with her, as he witneſſeth to the Corinthians: Therfore Chriſt is far from that Church in reſpect of any bleſſing or approving of their worſhip, howſoever Mr Brightman perſwaded otherwiſe: And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the two ſynns whereof he accuſed before that Angel of the Ch: of England, are here found upon him: namely that in thus writing he hath been both a perſecutor of the brethren and a deceiver of the Prince: for what greater perſecution could he put upon thoſe poore ſoules which have ſeparated themſelves from thoſe evills by himſelfe ſet down, then to accuſe or charge them of blaſphemy; yea it is ſuch a perſecution as that it is unto death; for by the lawe of God, a blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemer muſt dye. And how hath he alſo deceived the Princes he &amp; others of his minde by cauſing them to baniſh and keepe in baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment their moſt loyall and faithfull ſubjects? And in deed although I am but a ſtranger unto them and one of an other people, yet the truth cauſed me to ſpeak thus in their behalf, that I know not any people at this day under the Sunne more loyall and faithfull unto their Prince and country; and more zelous and religious towards God, then they are: and theſe things are ſeen in them and among them both privately and publikly: yea in ſuch meaſure as that, I am fully perſwaded that they are, and ſhalbe if they continue faithfull unto the end, that people by which cheifly Antichriſt the man of ſin ſhalbe rooted out: for by that purity of doctrine which they doe teach, &amp; by the ſyncere and publick adminiſtration of the glorious Kingdome of Chriſt publikly and before all the people; as alſo by profeſſing that glorious liberty in the Goſpel, that if any ſinne be ſhewed or manifeſted unto them by the word of God is amended whatſoever oppoſition may be to the contrary; by thoſe things, I ſay, by them profeſſed, practiſed, and taught, it is impoſſible that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:150666:8"/> where they have place, Antichriſt can or have any doore to come in. And for my part I doe bleſſe the day in which I had that grace from my God to knowe both the people &amp; their faithfull walking in their wayes and religion of God; and <hi>J beſech the Lord of his grace even with tears that he vouchſafe to open the eyes of their moſt noble and wiſe Prince that he may ſee the iustice and equity of their cauſe, and cauſe them to ſee his Royall face and preſence agayn with ioy and gladnes of heart under his dominions and iuriſdictions, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo I do here end, though many more things might be ſaid touching ſeparation from evil, and adjoyning or following that which is good: and in deed in a word, wee ſhall not read even from the beginning of the world to this day, that there was ever any true Church of God truely eſtabliſhed but by ſeparation: &amp; therfore this peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple not to be blaſphemers, but true worſhipers of GOD.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
